Guide to the Robert Hale Merriman and Marion Merriman Papers ALBA.191
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert Hale Merriman and Marion Merriman Papers
1922-1993
1934-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Merriman, Marion, 1909-
Merriman, Robert Hale
ALBA.191
8 Linear Feet in 5 record boxes and 4 oversized flat boxes.
Robert Hale Merriman (1908-1938) and his wife Marion Merriman (later Wachtel) served with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War. Robert served as first commander of the Lincolns and rose to the rank of chief of staff of the 15th International Brigade. Marion served the Brigade as a volunteer in several capacities. In November 1937, Marion returned to the United States to raise money for war by making speeches at rallies across the country. Robert disappeared during an ambush at Corbera (Ebro Valley) and his body was never found. Marion became active in the Bay Area Chapter of Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). Later in her life, she co-wrote American Commander in Spain: Robert Hale Merriman and the Abraham Lincoln Brigade with journalist Warren Lerude. Robert Jordan, the main character in For Whom the Bell Tolls – Ernest Hemingway's Spanish Civil War novel – was apparently modeled after Robert Merriman. This collection contains a small amount of material from the Spanish Civil War, including letters from Robert to Marion before Marion joined him in Spain and two diaries he kept in Spain. The bulk of the collection consists of organizational materials documenting Marion's involvement in the Bay Area chapter of VALB. Three typescript versions of American Commander in Spain and additional material related to the writing of the book are also included.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Robert Hale Merriman and Marion Merriman Papers (.25 ft.) were first donated to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The remaining Merriman papers held by the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA) were donated to Tamiment, via Peter Carroll in June 2006. The accession number associated with both of these donations is 2001.145. In 2015, Joe Wachtel sent 4 boxes of artifacts and clothing in 2015. The accession number associated with this gift is 2015.060. Joe Wachtel sent an additional 3 boxes of correspondence, clippings, and photographs in 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2016.071.
Arrangement
Folders in series I-IV are arranged alphabetically. Materials in Series V: 2016 Accretion have not been arranged by an archivist and are in the order in which they were received from the donor.
The series arrangement of the collection is as follows:
Series I: Spanish Civil War and Earlier, 1932-1937. Series II: Subject Files, 1946-1993. Series III: Files relating to American Commander in Spain: Robert Hale Merriman and the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1982-1987. Series IV: Artifacts, 1922-1933. Series V: 2016 Accretion
Historical/Biographical Note
Robert Hale Merriman (1908-1938) was a graduate student in economics at the University of California at Berkeley when he became interested in Russian economics. He had met his future wife Marion Stone when both were undergraduates at the University of Nevada; they married on their graduation day, May 9, 1932. The Merrimans moved to Moscow in January 1935. An excursion to Vienna gave Robert and Marion a firsthand view of Nazism and motivated Robert, who had received some basic military training in ROTC as a undergraduate at the University of Nevada, to join the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in 1937. In Spain, Robert trained other U.S. volunteers and eventually rose to the rank of chief of staff of the 15th International Brigade. At first, Marion remained in Moscow, working for a New York Times correspondent Walter Duranty. She came to Spain in March of 1937 to tend to Robert after he was wounded by a gunshot to the shoulder in the Battle of Jarama. After his recovery, Marion remained in Spain and served the brigade as a clerk. Marion also worked in a hospital, held various staff jobs, collected information for death certificates, and led tours for visiting celebrities. She was eventually promoted to the rank of corporal. In November 1937, Marion returned to the United States to raise money for the cause. She made numerous speeches at rallies across the country and returned to San Francisco in March 1938, where she worked as a secretary for a group raising medical aid for the Loyalists.
After Robert Merriman disappeared, during an ambush at Corbera (Ebro Valley), conflicting reports stated that he was being held by fascist forces or that he had been killed. Unsuccessful appeals were made urging the U. S. State Department to press for his release, including a petition from UC Berkeley professors and UC President Robert Gordon Sproul. Merriman's body was never found but by 1938 he was presumed dead.
Marion was eventually remarried, to attorney Emil Wachtel. She had three sons with Wachtel, who died in 1977. She held various jobs throughout her life and continued for many years to be active in the Bay Area Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). She took several trips to Spain after the death of Francisco Franco, and worked strenuously to keep Robert Merriman's memory alive. Later in her life, she co-wrote American Commander in Spain: Robert Hale Merriman and the Abraham Lincoln Brigade(University of Nevada Press, 1986) with journalist and University of Nevada faculty member Warren Lerude. Robert Jordan, the main character in For Whom the Bell Tolls– Ernest Hemingway's Spanish Civil War novel – was apparently modeled after Robert Merriman.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains a small amount of material from the Spanish Civil War including two of Robert Merriman's diaries and letters from Robert to Marion Merriman before she joined him in Spain. The bulk of the collection consists of materials related to the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). Marion Merriman corresponded with and collected material on many Lincoln veterans. There is also organizational material from the national office and Bay Area chapter of VALB. Files related to the writing of American Commander in Spain include notes, correspondence, three typescript versions (an early draft, an edited version and a final manuscript), reviews, publicity material and letters from readers. Artifacts (Series IV) consist of two printed items owned by Robert before the Spanish Civil War, a belt worn by Marion and two hats and six garments owned by Robert in the Spanish Civil War years. Additional clippings, articles, photographs, and correspondence regarding Robert and Marion Merriman's experience during the Spanish Civil War and the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades are included in Series V: 2016 Accretion. These materials include drafts of Marion Merriman's writings, newspaper clippings regarding Robert's disappearance and death, and an assortment of articles and newsletters about Lincoln Brigade veterans. They also include photographs of Robert and Marion Merriman in the 1930s, and photos of Marion as late as the 1980s. These materials also include 2 undated audio recordings of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades.
Separated Material
Photographs and audiotapes from the Robert Hale Merriman Papers have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collections in the Tamiment Library.
Issues of The Volunteer donated in 2016 were separated and added to Tamiment's periodicals collections.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Literature and the war.; Research (document genres).; Drafts (documents); Belchite (Spain) -- History -- Siege, 1937.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Articles.; Biography files.; Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Personal papers.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Brunete, Battle of, Brunete, Spain, 1937.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Barcelona (Spain); Madrid (Spain); Murcia (Spain); Jarama River Valley (Spain); Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Lerude, Warren, 1937-; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Bay Area Post; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Merriman, Robert Hale; Merriman, Marion, 1909-; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy
- Series I: Spanish Civil War and Earlier, 1932-1937.
  - Correspondence from Robert Merriman to Marion Merriman, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from Robert Merriman to Marion Merriman, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - RHM Diaries (2 volumes), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1946-1993.
  - Bailey, Bill, 1984, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Baley, Barney, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Barsky, Vita, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bay Area Post, Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Al Stanley Scholarship Fund – La Cheim School, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bay Area Post, VALB: Executive Board Meetings, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bay Area Post, VALB: Newspaper Clippings, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bay Area Post, VALB: Veterans Rights Committee, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bender, Ed, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bertelli and Nuwer, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bessie, Alvah, 1970-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Brown, Archie: Retirement Testimonial Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chipp, Herschel, 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Colodny, Robert, 1966-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Corbin, Rudy, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Ducan, Faiga, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Eloesser, Leo, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Entwistle, Tom, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Esteban, Fausto Villar, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Geiser, Carl, 1978-1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hene, Julius, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Iceland, Ben, undated, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Lamb, Leonard, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Law, Norman, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lucid, Jack, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Martin, Fredricka, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Mates, Dave, 1977-1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - McLeod, Don, 1979, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Nelson, Steve, 1976-1993 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Newan, Roby, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Powell, Bill and Sylvia, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Prago, Albert, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Reed, Robert, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Rodriguez, Gabriel Salinas, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Rolfe, Edwin, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Simon, Mildred Rackley, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Smith, Randall B. (Pete), 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Spanish Refugee Appeal, 1946-1954 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Speigel, Irene Golden, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Tisa, John, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - U.S. Committee for a Democratic Spain, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB), 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - VALB, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - VALB, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - VALB, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - VALB, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - VALB, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - VALB, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - VALB, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - VALB, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - VALB, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - VALB, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - VALB, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - VALB, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - VALB, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - VALB: Administrative Committee, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - VALB: Anniversary (50th), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - VALB: Anniversary Dinners, 1973-1986 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - VALB: Mailing List, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - VALB: National Board, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - VALB: Organizational Material, 1971-1982 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - VALB: Speeches, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Wheeler, Bill, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Wolff, Milt, 1975-1984 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Series III: Files Relating to American Commander in Spain: Robert Merriman and the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1982-1987.
  - Background Material, Notes, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bancroft Library, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dust Jacket, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Foreign Editions, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Readers, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript: Edited (Chapter 1-13), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript: Edited (Chapter 14 – Notes and Bibliography), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript: Edited (Chapter 1-24), Apr 1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript: Edited (Chapter 25 – Epilogue), Apr 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript: Final (Photo Credits, Chapters 1-8), Sep 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript: Final (Chapters 9-16), Sep 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript: Final (Chapter 17 – Epilogue, notes, Bibliography, Sep 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript: Unedited (Prologue, Chapters 1-17), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript: Unedited (Chapters 18-24), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Preface Dedication, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Publicity, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Publishers: Correspondence with, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Reviews, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - University of Nevada Press, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Artifacts, 1922-1933
  - California Chinese Chatter, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Marion Merriman's Belt, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Modern Postage Stamp Album, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Beaded Silk Hat and Black Velvet Hat, Circa 1932-1938 (Box 3)
  - Black Wool Coat and Gray/Brown Wool Coat, undated (Box 4)
  - Multicolored Silk Jacket and Blue Silk Robe, undated (Box 5)
  - Padded Blue Silk Robe and Cream Silk Robe, undated (Box 6)
- 2016 Accretion
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains an assortment of documents and articles collected by Marion Merriman about her late husband Robert Hale Merriman. These materials largely consist of articles and essays about Robert Merriman's service with the Abraham Lincoln Brigades in Spain and stories about his death in 1938. They include newspaper clippings from the 1930s as well as articles and essays written about Robert and Marion Merriman in the 1970s and 1980s. The collection contains several photographs of Robert and Marion Merriman in Spain during the war as well as photographs of Marion later in her life. The series includes several files of newspaper clippings, scholarly articles, and essays about the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades (VALB) that Marion Merriman collected in the years after the Spanish Civil War. Several files relate to Marion's work on her 1986 biography of Robert, American Commander in Spain, which she wrote with Warren Larude. Also included in the series are transcripts of Robert's diaries, photocopies of his letter letters, a scrapbook of clippings about the Spanish Civil War, and two audio reels of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades.
  - Robert Merriman Education and Military Service, 1932-1934, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Marion Merrman Wachtel Writings, 1948-1956, undated (Box 7)
  - Robert and Marion Merriman Photographs, circa 1930-1980 (Box 7)
  - Mac-Paps News Bulletin, 1975-1981 (Box 7)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Clippings and Research Files, 1936-1986 (Box 7, Box 8)
  - Scholarly Articles on the Spanish Civil War, 1939-1986 (Box 8)
  - Robert Merriman Diary Transcripts, 1980 (Box 8)
  - Lists of American Volunteers in Spain, 1983-1985 (Box 8)
  - Spanish Civil War Scrapbook, 1937-1938 (Box 9)
  - Audio Recordings - Spain, undated (Box 9)